Guide to the Mary Smyth Hunter Correspondence
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Mary Smyth Hunter correspondence
1895-1940
OSB MSS 186
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
2.71
(7 boxes)
Autograph manuscript letters and postcards, mostly signed, addressed to Mary Smyth Hunter and to two of her descendants, her daughter Cary Phyllis (Hunter) Williamson, and her grand-daughter Elizabeth Williamson. Major correspondents include Maurice Baring, Max Beerbohm, Gabriel Fauré, Edmund Gosse, Edvard Grieg, George Henschel, Henry James, William James, Claude Monet, George Moore, Auguste Rodin, John Singer Sargent, Henry Tonks, Edith Wharton, and Virginia Woolf. The collection also features approximately 275 pieces of correspondence to Elizabeth Williamson from Mary Smyth Hunter's sister, the composer and suffragist Ethel Smyth.
Hunter, Mary Smyth, 1856-1933
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Purchased from Joan Winterkorn on the James Marshall and Marie-Louise Osborn Collection Fund, 2013.
Information About Access
This collection is open for research.
Mary Smyth Hunter (1856-1933)
Mary (Smyth) Hunter (1856-1933), born in India to Major General John Smyth (1815-1894) and Nina (Struth) Smyth, married the wealthy coal-mining heir Charles Edward Hunter in 1875. Mary was known for her lavish hospitality at Hill Hall, their country house near Epping, in Essex county, England, and for her patronage of musicians, writers, and artists.
Description of the Papers
Autograph manuscript letters and postcards, mostly signed, addressed to Mary Smyth Hunter and to two of her descendants, her daughter Cary Phyllis (Hunter) Williamson, and her grand-daughter Elizabeth Williamson. Major correspondents include Maurice Baring, Max Beerbohm, Gabriel Fauré, Edmund Gosse, Edvard Grieg, George Henschel, Henry James, William James, Claude Monet, George Moore, Auguste Rodin, John Singer Sargent, Henry Tonks, Edith Wharton, and Virginia Woolf. The collection also features approximately 275 pieces of correspondence to Elizabeth Williamson from Mary Smyth Hunter's younger sister, the composer and suffragist Ethel Smyth.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Letters to Mary Smyth Hunter, 1895-1935. II. Letters to Elizabeth Williamson, 1923-1940. III. Letters to Phyllis Williamson, 1898-1936.
Composers -- England -- Correspondence; Country life -- Great Britain; Great Britain -- Social life and customs -- 20th Century; Composers -- England -- 20th Century; Baring, Maurice, 1874-1945; Beerbohm, Max, Sir, 1872-1956; Fauré, Gabriel, 1845-1924; Gosse, Edmund, 1849-1928; Grieg, Edvard, 1843-1907; Henschel, George, 1850-1934; Hunter, Mary Smyth, 1856-1933; James, Henry, 1843-1916; James, William, 1842-1910; Monet, Claude, 1840-1926; Moore, George, 1852-1933; Rodin, Auguste, 1840-1917; Sargent, John Singer, 1856-1925; Smyth, Ethel, 1858-1944; Tonks, Henry, 1862-1937; Wharton, Edith, 1862-1937; Woolf, Virginia, 1882-1941
- Letters to Mary Smyth Hunter, 1895-1935; Series I; 1.04; 3 boxes
  Arrangement
  Arranged alphabetically.
  Scope and Contents
  Series I. consists of letters to Mary Smyth Hunter. Larger files can be found for Henry James, Claude Monet, George Moore, John Singer Sargent, and for Mary's younger sister, the composer and suffragist Ethel Smyth. Other correspondents include Max Beerbohm, Gabriel Fauré, Edmund Gosse, Edvard Grieg, George Henschel, William James, Auguste Rodin, and Edith Wharton.
  - Abbey, Edwin A., undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Aitken, Charles, 1929 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Arthur, Prince, Duke of Connaught, 1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Balfour, A. J., 1895-1901 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Beerbohm, Max, Sir, 1913-1919 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Blanche, Jacques-Émile, [1895?], undated (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Boldini, Giovanni, 1902-1903, undated (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Brabazon, Hercules Brabazon, 1898, undated (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Brown, Henry Harris, 1904, undated (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Carr, J. Comyns (Joseph Comyns), undated (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Chamberlain, Austen, 1902-1906 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Charteris, Evan, 1917 May 20 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Dayot, Armand, 1909, undated (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Fauré, Gabriel, undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Fildes, Luke, Sir, [1901?] April 4 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Fisher, Mark, 1917, undated (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - French, ----, 1902 July 16 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - French, [John, Viscount], 1916, 1919 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Gosse, Edmund, 1900, 1916 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Grieg, Edvard, 1896 February 11 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Guthrie, James, 1903, 1905 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Harris, Frank, 1904 April 25 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Helleu, Paul, undated (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Henschel, George, 1902, 1917 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Henschel, Lillian B., no year September 26 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - James, Alice H[owe Gibbons?], 1910 August 10 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - James, Henry, 1903-1912 (Box 1, Folder 27-33)
  - James, Henry, 1913-1915 (Box 2, Folder 34-35)
  - James, William, 1910 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  - John, Augustus, no year April 20 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  - La Farge, John, 1906 August 15 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  - Lascelles, Frank C., 1898 April 30 (Box 2, Folder 39)
  - Lavery, John, 1904 May 3 (Box 2, Folder 40)
  - Lee, Vernon, 1917, undated (Box 2, Folder 41)
  - Louise Margaret, Princess, Duchess of Connaught, undated (Box 2, Folder 42)
  - Lubbock, Percy, 1920, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 43)
  - Lutyens, Edwin L., 1915 [July?] 30 (Box 2, Folder 44)
  - Mancini, Antonio, 1902-1903, undated (Box 2, Folder 45)
  - Melba, Nellie, undated (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Meynell, Alice, undated (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Meynell, Wilfrid, undated (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Monet, Claude, 1900-1913, undated (Box 2, Folder 49-50)
  - Moore, George, 1896-1932, undated (Box 2, Folder 51-54)
  - Orpen, William, Sir, undated (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Parsons, Alfred, 1898-1917, undated (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Poynter, Edward J[ohn], 1903-1906 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Richmond, W. B., undated (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Ricketts, C[harles], undated (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Ridley, Matthew White, Sir, 1899-1900, undated (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Rodd, Rennell, undated (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Rodin, Auguste, 1903-1915, undated (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Rothenstein, William, 1904, undated (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Sargent, John Singer, 1901-1918, undated (Box 2, Folder 64-66)
  - Shannon, C. L., 1899 April 26 (Box 3, Folder 67)
  - Smyth, Ethel, 1912, undated (Box 3, Folder 68-69)
  - Steer, Philip Wilson, 1917-1931, undated (Box 3, Folder 70)
  - Swann, John M., 1900-1902 (Box 3, Folder 71)
  - Swynnerton, Annie, 1914-1916, undated (Box 3, Folder 72)
  - Swynnerton, Joseph W., 1906 May 18 (Box 3, Folder 73)
  - Symons, Will C., no year November 13 (Box 3, Folder 74)
  - Thornycroft, William Hamo, Sir, undated (Box 3, Folder 75)
  - Tonks, Henry, 1912-1936 (Box 3, Folder 76)
  - Warner, Joseph D., 1906 July 19 (Box 3, Folder 77)
  - Wharton, Edith, 1915 December (Box 3, Folder 78)
  - Others, 1897-1935, undated (Box 3, Folder 79-81)
  - "Book catalogue: Vol I", circa 1916-1917 (Box 3, Folder 82)
  - Clipping, undated (Box 3, Folder 83)
  - List of guests, 1915 May 15 (Box 3, Folder 84)
  - Photographs, 1915, undated (Box 3, Folder 85)
  - Writings, 1904, undated (Box 3, Folder 86)
- Letters to Elizabeth Williamson, 1923-1940; Series II; 0.84; 2 boxes
  Series II. consists of letters to Elizabeth Williamson. The series features approximately 275 pieces of correspondence, including both autograph letters and postcards, signed, from Elizabeth's great aunt, the composer and sugffragist Ethel Smyth. There are also letters from Maurice Baring, Ariana Wormeley Curtis, George Moore, Henry Tonks, and Virginia Woolf.
  - Baring, Maurice, 1926-1934 (Box 4, Folder 87)
  - Curtis, Ariana Wormeley, no year October 24 (Box 4, Folder 88)
  - Moore, George, 1927 August 27 (Box 4, Folder 89)
  - Smyth, Ethel, 1925-1932 (Box 4, Folder 90-101)
  - Smyth, Ethel, 1932-1935 (Box 5, Folder 102-112)
  - Smyth, Ethel, 1935-1939, undated (Box 6, Folder 113-123)
  - Tonks, Henry, 1923-1933 (Box 6, Folder 124)
  - Woolf, Virginia, 1931-1940, undated (Box 6, Folder 125)
  - Others, 1932-1938, undated (Box 6, Folder 126)
- Letters to Phyllis Williamson, 1898-1936; Series III; 0.42; 1 box
  Series III. consists of letters to Phyllis Williamson. Larger files can be found for George Moore and Henry Tonks. Other correspondents include George Henschel, Joseph M. Hone, and Alfred Sutro.
  - Bloomfield, Reginald, 1920 March 30 (Box 7, Folder 127)
  - Clarke, Margaret E., 1919 December 10 (Box 7, Folder 128)
  - Dunedin, [A. Graham Murray (Andrew Graham Murray), Viscount,?], 1915 November 9 (Box 7, Folder 129)
  - French, John, Viscount, 1916 May 20 (Box 7, Folder 130)
  - [Hamilton, Ian?], 1922 November 17 (Box 7, Folder 131)
  - Henschel, George, 1900 April 4 (Box 7, Folder 132)
  - Hone, Joseph [M. (Joseph Maunsell)?], 1935-1936 (Box 7, Folder 133)
  - James, C. W., undated (Box 7, Folder 134)
  - Mallock, W. H., 1921 March 9 (Box 7, Folder 135)
  - Moore, George, 1898-1930, undated (Box 7, Folder 136-140)
  - Morgan, Charles, 1933 March 13 (Box 7, Folder 141)
  - Ross, Robert, 1918 October 2 (Box 7, Folder 142)
  - Sutro, Alfred, 1922 [November?] 13 (Box 7, Folder 143)
  - Swynnerton, Annie, no year October 3 (Box 7, Folder 144)
  - Tonks, Henry, 1929-1936 (Box 7, Folder 145-147)
  - Tweed, John, 1918 May 26 (Box 7, Folder 148)
  - Wood, Evelyn, 1914, undated (Box 7, Folder 149)
  - Others, 1915-1916, undated (Box 7, Folder 150)